Well right, so that becomes part of the question exactly. Part of...
good. So,
the morning, today is the 6th of January, it's the 8th of
טבת. Tevet. I'm Dan Margulies filling in for Rabbi Linzer while he's
still away. He's teaching a lot of תורה. Torah. And today's דף
Daf is בבא מציעא Bava Metziah קב. Kuf Bet. We'll start right
from the top line. The גמרא Gemara says: תנו רבנן המשכיר בית
לחבירו, Tanu Rabbanan HaMaskir Bayit LeChavero, someone rents a house to someone
else, על השוכר לעשות לו מזוזה, Al HaSocher LaAsot Lo Mezuzah,
so the renter has the responsibility to put up the מזוזה. Mezuzah.
מזוזה, Mezuzah, of course, here referring not to the decorative box, but
to the actual מזוזה, Mezuzah, the scroll. People often get a little
bit confused about that. וכשהוא יוצא לא יטלנה בידו. U'ChsheHu Yotze Lo
Yittalena BeYado.
The renter who moves out, this is very important for rental properties
and apartments, this is what David was just asking. The person who
put up the מזוזה Mezuzah is actually not supposed to take the
מזוזה Mezuzah with him. לא יטלנה בידו ויצא. Lo Yittalena BeYado VeYotze.
ומנכרי, U'miNochri, but if you're... if it's going to a non-Jewish renter
next, נוטלה בידו ויצא, Notla BeYado VeYotze, then you can take it
in your hand when you leave. ומעשה באחד שנטלה בידו ויצא, U'Maaseh
Be'Echad SheNatla BeYado VeYatza, and there was a case of someone who
inappropriately took the מזוזה Mezuzah with him when he left, וקבר אשתו
ושני בניו, VeKavar Ishto VeShenei Vanav, his wife and two children predeceased
him, a very tragic story. מעשה לסתור, Maaseh LeSstor, so is the
purpose of the story being quoted to contradict? אמר
רב ששת ארישא. Amar Rav Sheshet Arisha. No, no, no, it's not
saying coming to contradict about if a non-Jewish person is renting the
apartment after you that you should leave up the מזוזה. Mezuzah. It's
not what it's coming to say. All it's coming to confirm the
רישא. Reisha. That is, when you're renting it to a Jewish person
afterwards, you should leave up the מזוזות. Mezuzot. Part of the complication
with הלכות מזוזה Hilkhot Mezuzah is that there are some differences, particularly
about rental properties between ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and חוץ לארץ, Chutz
La'Aretz, and so that can complicate things, particularly about for how much
time after you move in do you have a grace period before
you have to put up the מזוזות Mezuzot and things like that.
And as far as this הלכה, Halakha, generally the sense is if
you know for sure that there's a Jewish person who's going to
be moving in after you, then it's a good thing to, you
know, not just a good thing, the הלכה Halakha is that you
should leave up the מזוזות. Mezuzot. The recommendation I've heard is take
down actually the decorative cases because those can be pretty pricey and
leave up the מזוזה Mezuzah itself, and when you move into your
next apartment you'll get new מזוזות. Mezuzot. Still, a good quality מזוזה
Mezuzah could be between, you know, twenty and fifty dollars sometimes, so,
you know, depends. But that's something, you know, important for the reason.
The reason why should you have to leave up the מזוזה Mezuzah
when one person is moving out and one person is moving in?
So תוספות's Tosafot suggestion is that it has to do with that
there are מזיקין Mazikin who are going to come into the house
when there are no מזוזות. Mezuzot. מזיקין, Mazikin, some kind of demons.
The ריטב"א Ritva takes it sort of more the positive side, that
when the מזוזה Mezuzah is on the house, God's שכינה Shekhinah is
protecting or dwelling within the house, and therefore removing that מזוזה Mezuzah
is taking away God's שכינה Shekhinah from dwelling in the house. We
want to always increase the places where God's presence can be felt
and not decrease it. Yeah. So my question was like in the
general, in our living situations, we don't know who's going to move
into the apartment, whether it's a Jew or non-Jew. Right. So what
do people usually do? So then generally I would think that in
those kinds of cases people would take down the מזוזות Mezuzot when
they move out. That's the sense that I would have, unless you
know for sure that it's a Jewish person, just because the concerns,
the motivating value is also to make sure that the מזוזה Mezuzah
isn't thrown into the trash or something like that. So that would
be a concern. Do you have anything to say about the term
נכרי, Nochri, as these are places where נכרי Nochri was not changed
by the censors to עובד כוכבים ומזלות? Oved Kokhavim U'Mazalot? Is there...
Because here it's... here there's nothing derogatory about the use of the
word נכרי. Nochri. Many of the other places where non-Jewish people are
mentioned in the גמרא, Gemara, it was changed to עכו"ם. Akkum. Like
this, a non-Jewish person is not going to be offended, like, "Oh,
they took down the מזוזה." Mezuzah. Like, okay, because that's their Jewish
thing, and they took it down because I'm moving into the house.
That's fine. I listened to this podcast today, nobody took down their
מזוזה. Mezuzah.
They leave them up, you mean? They leave them up. Wonderful. Good.
Is it that everybody's Jewish, or...? Or you assume everybody's taking good
care of the מזוזה, Mezuzah, I don't know. Or maybe the owner
of the building is Jewish and therefore,
you know, that's the other question, is here we're talking about, you
know, someone rents a single house. But what if the שוכר Sokher
owns many apartments in the same building? You know, presumably, even once
people move into individual apartments, but perhaps you would say the whole...
the whole responsibility lies on the שוכר. Sokher. That's part of this
question here as well. Like why is it that the שוכר Sokher
is the one with the liability, not liability, responsibility to put up
the מזוזה? Mezuzah? So רש"י Rashi here seems to say that the
argument is based on who goes in. Who goes through the door,
so to say. The person who's living in the house, that's gonna
be the person who has the—it's not רש״י Rashi here, it's רש״י
Rashi in other גמרות gemaras that talk about מזוזה mezuzah like in
פסחים. Pesachim. פסחים דף ד׳. Pesachim Daf Daled. Yeah. So רש״י, Rashi,
it's the רש״י Rashi in פסחים. Pesachim. Okay. So the next clause
of the משנה: mishna: הזבל של בעל הבית, Ha-zevel shel ba'al habayit,
the manure that's produced belongs to the בעל הבית, ba'al habayit, ואין
לשוכר אלא היוצא מן התנור ומן הכיריים בלבד, ve-ein la-socher ella ha-yotzei
min ha-tannur u-min ha-kiirayim bilvad, but the thing that the שוכר socher
gets is are the ashes that are left over from the use
of the תנור tannur מן הכיריים בלבד min ha-kiirayim bilvad that are
in the חצר. chatzer. That is, what was the case? The case
was really that you rented not the—not the חצר, chatzer, but you
only rented the—the house. And the house has certain permission to use
the חצר chatzer to put animals there, to use the oven that's
there, but you don't actually get a rental claim on the חצר
chatzer itself as a whole. So the זבל, zevel, whatever manure is
produced into the חצר chatzer would—should go to whomever owns the חצר.
chatzer. So we're going to see the גמרא gemara has some questions
about that. And then about the תנור, tannur, well if you burn
your own wood in the תנור, tannur, well the ashes should still
belong to you, right?
Okay. במאי עסקינן, Bemai askinan, what case are we talking about? אילימא
בחצר דאגירה ליה לשוכר ותורי דשוכר, Ilima b'chatzer d'agira leh l'socher v'torei
d'socher, well are we talking about if the חצר chatzer was rented
to the person renting the house and the animals in the חצר
chatzer also belong to the שוכר, socher, so אמאי של בעל הבית,
amai shel ba'al habayit, then why should the manure belong to the
בעל הבית? ba'al habayit? The rights for the חצר chatzer would belong
to the שוכר socher and the animal itself belongs to the שוכר,
socher, should belong to the שוכר. socher. אלא בחצר דלא אגירה לשוכר
ותורי דמשכיר, Ella b'chatzer d'lo agira l'socher v'torei d'maskir, but then are
we talking about a case of where the חצר chatzer was not
rented to the שוכר, socher, it remains in the control of the
משכיר maskir and the animals also belong to the משכיר, maskir, so
פשיטא, pshita, that's also an obvious case. Of course that would belong
to
בעל הבית. ba'al habayit. Okay. לא צריכא בחצר דמשכיר ותורי דאתו מעלמא.
Lo tzericha b'chatzer d'maskir v'torei d'atu m'alma. So—so—so ותורי דאתו מעלמא, v'torei
d'atu m'alma, so ותורי דאתו מעלמא, v'torei d'atu m'alma, and animals, oxen
from someone else's animals walked into the חצר. chatzer. The חצר chatzer
is not being rented out, it's still under the control of the
original owner, and in that case the manure will belong to the
owner and not to the person renting the house. So if someone
else's animal deposited something in my חצר, chatzer, I get to keep
it. Now what's the הוה אמינא? hava amina? The הוה אמינא hava
amina is that the שוכר socher of the house could still have
some use of the חצר chatzer and presumably if he's in the
חצר chatzer and he would come and pick up, scoop up the
manure before the owner was aware of it, maybe he should be
allowed to do that because it was הפקר, hefker, right? It was
totally ownerless manure, you know people don't really own manure. But the
חצר chatzer was קונה koneh but he was the שוכר. socher. Exactly.
So the חצר chatzer of the בעל הבית, ba'al habayit, the original
owner's control of the property has a קנין חצר. kinyan chatzer. So
now we have to see. So the גמרא gemara suggests: מסייע ליה
לרבי יוסי ברבי חנינא. Mesaye leh l'Rabbi Yosi b'Rabbi Chanina. Maybe this
will support the opinion of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi the son of
רבי חנינא. Rabbi Chanina. Why? דאמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא חצרו של
אדם קונה לו שלא מדעתו. D'amar Rabbi Yosi b'Rabbi Chanina chatzero shel
adam kona lo shelo mida'ato. A person's property, a person's חצר chatzer
can acquire something ownerless on their behalf even without their knowledge. That
is when the animal deposits the manure in the
חצר, chatzer, the manure will be acquired by the בעל הבית ba'al
habayit even without his knowledge. And therefore that would take place regardless
of whether the שוכר socher had any intent or attempt to try
to claim it first.
So מיתיבי, meitivei, but we should challenge that idea. אם אמר כל
מציאות שיבוא לתוכו היום תקני לי חצרי. Im amar kol metziot sheyavo
l'tocho hayom tikni li chatzeri. What if someone said, any lost objects
that come into my חצר chatzer today should be acquired for me
by my חצר? chatzer? לא אמר כלום, Lo amar klum, he didn't
say anything. It's a meaningless statement. Okay. ואם
איתא להא דאמר רבי יוסי ברבי—so V'im ita l'ha d'amar Rabbi Yosi
b'Rabbi but why? That's because the חצר chatzer that we're talking about
in that case is a חצר chatzer that was not a חצר
המשתמרת. chatzer hamishtameret. It wasn't a חצר chatzer that was actually well—well
enclosed.
Sorry I was trying to look for the רש״י, Rashi, I fell
farther down the page.
Sorry. Okay, the גמרא gemara is going to explain it a little
bit more.
Okay. דאמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא חצרו של אדם קונה לו שלא
מדעתו. D'amar Rabbi Yosi b'Rabbi Chanina chatzero shel adam kona lo shelo
mida'ato. If you're going to tell me that רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא
Rabbi Yosi b'Rabbi Chanina is correct, that is this ברייתא braita is
being used to challenge רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא's Rabbi Yosi b'Rabbi Chanina
opinion, so אמאי לא אמר כלום? amai lo amar klum? So of
course, because רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא Rabbi Yosi b'Rabbi Chanina said it
could, חצרו של אדם קונה לו שלא מדעתו. Chatzero shel adam kona
lo shelo mida'ato. If the חצר chatzer could acquire— for you without
your knowledge then why of course it should acquire for you even
if you didn't say anything. So what does it mean you didn't
say anything? You didn't say anything means it's ineffective even if you
did say something but it sounds like it would be effective even
if you didn't say something. He says the opposite. Okay, so בהכא
במאי עסקינן, be-hacha b'mai askinan, what are we talking about? בחצר שאינה
משתמרת. b'chatzer she'eina mishtameret. It was a חצר chatzer that was not
well enclosed or was not well guarded in such a way that
whatever lost object fell in there someone else might come by and
pick it up. So the idea of a קניין חצר kinyan chatzer
is the חצר chatzer could only be קונה koneh if it's a
חצר המשתמרת. chatzer hamishtameret. It's a חצר chatzer that is fenced in,
fenced in in such a way that the owner has not only
that the idea of the קניין חצר kinyan chatzer isn't just that
there's like a magic power that your property kind of acquire things
that land on it, but that the presumption or the understanding that
if something ownerless lands in your field no one else is going
to try to come get it first or you'll be able to
retain control of it. That's the idea of ownership is that it's
in a place where you have control. So that's the idea of
the חצר המשתמרת. chatzer hamishtameret. So
אי הכי, ei hachi, אימא סיפא: eima seifa: יצא לו שם מציאה
בעיר, yatzah lo shem metziah ba'ir, דבריו קיימין. devarav kayamin. But then
what about the second clause of that ברייתא braita which we're only
just reading now? That is, if people were talking about it in
town that this object got lost,
then his statement is binding. So what does that mean? That is,
a person had a חצר שאינה משתמרת. chatzer she'eina mishtameret. It was
not well enclosed. Then he announced, any מציאה metziah that lands in
my field today should be acquired for me by my field and
then something fell into the field. So why should that work? So
אי בחצר שאינה משתמרת, ei b'chatzer she'eina mishtameret, כי יצא לו שם
מציאה בעיר, ki yatzah lo shem metziah ba'ir, מאי הוי? mai havay?
What does that mean? So still it's a חצר chatzer that's not
well guarded, so why should it matter? כיון דיצא לו שם מציאה
בעיר, keivan d'yatzah lo shem metziah ba'ir, מיבדל בדילי אינשי מיניה. mibdal
bdili inshi minei. No, because as soon as people are talking about
it that such and such lost animal or lost object landed in
this field,
and even though it's not well guarded, but the fact that people
are talking about it, people will distance themselves from that field. They're
not going to try to go into it. והויא לה כחצר המשתמרת.
ve-havaia lah ke-chatzer hamishtameret. And then it becomes like a משתמרת. mishtameret.
That is, it's not an objective case of חצר המשתמרת; chatzer hamishtameret;
it has a good fence around it, but it has a psychological
fence. People are not going to go into my field to take
something as soon as people in town are talking about it. Why?
Because that object, that ownerless object already landed in my field or
that ownerless deer walked into my field. Now people are going to
keep away because they're going to know I sort of have a
first claim on it even though because I made that announcement, I
want my field to acquire it for me. So then we saw
there was an attempt to say רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא'ס Rabbi Yossi
berabbi Chanina's opinion fits with our משנה. mishna. Then we said, well,
maybe this other ברייתא braita contradicts. We said no, that ברייתא braita
doesn't necessarily contradict. It's a different kind of a scenario. So we
have another challenge. We want to challenge רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא'ס Rabbi
Yossi berabbi Chanina's position again. So מיתיבי, meitivei, there's another challenge: זבל
היוצא מן התנור ומן הכירה zevel hayotzei min hatannur u'min hakira והקולט
מן האויר ve-hakoleit min ha-avir הרי הוא שלו. harei hu shelo. So
this is similar or based off of our משנה mishna in some
sense.
The manure or whatever comes out of the oven and the stove
and הקולט מן האויר, hakoleit min ha-avir, anything that's snatched out of
the air, those things belong to him. That is whom? The person
who's renting the property. Okay, so that sounds like
not like what our משנה mishna was talking about.
Okay, ובשרפת ובחצר של בעל הבית u'vi-shreifat u've-chatzer shel ba'al habayit and
things that are in the stables or in the חצר, chatzer, the
courtyard of the בעל הבית. ba'al habayit. ואי איתא להא דרבי יוסי
ברבי חנינא, ve-i ita leha de-Rabbi Yossi berabbi Chanina, and if you're
going to tell me that רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא'ס Rabbi Yossi berabbi
Chanina's position applies, דאמר חצרו של אדם קונה לו שלא מדעתו, de-amar
chatzero shel adam koneh lo shelo mida'ato, because he said that the
חצר chatzer could acquire for you without your knowledge, קולט מאויר אמאי?
koleit me-avir amaye? Why should grabbing something out of the air belong
to the person renting the property? הרי הוא שלו? harei hu shelo?
Because the ברייתא braita says that. אויר חצרו הוא, avir chatzero hu,
but the airspace of the חצר chatzer is like the חצר chatzer
itself. Now this is of course a מחלוקת machloket which occupies much
of מסכת שבת. Masechet Shabbat. Yeah, well בבא קמא Bava Kamma we
saw, בבא בתרא Bava Batra for sure, בבא קמא Bava Kamma we
saw with the knife falling off of the off of the edge
of the wall, right? ושבת ve-Shabbat and שבת, Shabbat, all sorts of
cases of throwing things on שבת. Shabbat. So the idea that the
airspace is still considered to be part of the the ground space.
So אויר חצרו הוא avir chatzero hu and therefore what do you
mean grabbing it from the air belongs to whoever grabs it? No,
grabbing something from the air should count as whoever owns the חצר
chatzer and it should still belong to the owner of the חצר
chatzer because it's קונה לו שלא מדעתו. koneh lo shelo mida'ato. He
can acquire it even without his knowledge and therefore even if it's
in the air, it doesn't matter. So אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, so
what does אביי Abaye say? It must be במדביק כלי בשולי פרה.
bemadbik kli b'shulei para. If someone put a, you maybe have seen
this with the horses who pull the carriages in Central Park. Someone
puts a container directly underneath the cow to catch the manure, and
therefore, there was no time at which it was in the air.
It went directly from the cow into the container. And that's different
than it was in midair and then you grabbed it before it
landed on the ground. And that's the idea. Now, of course, manure
is not the most valuable thing in the world, but it's certainly
worth something. Okay. אמר אביי. Amar Abaye. So רבא אמר, Rava amar,
אויר שאין סופו לנוח לאו כמונח דמי. avir she'ein sofo lanuach lav
k'munach dami. רבא Rava disagrees. רבא Rava doesn't say it's based on
kind of a מציאות metziut problem, a different kind of a case.
רבא Rava is saying, no, the fact that someone was able to
interrupt its travel in midair indicates or disrupts the notion that the
אויר avir is part of the חצר. chatzer. This gets into the
question from הלכות שבת, Hilchot Shabbat,
the principle קלוטה כמי שהונחה דמיא, klutah k'mi shehunchah damya, something that
is passing through the air is as if it's already resting on
the ground. And that's an extended debate in the ראשונים Rishonim how
to understand that and what does that mean? Do we imagine that
the ground comes up to meet it? Do we imagine the object
is as if transported down onto the ground? All sorts of different
possibilities.
But one of the examples, so here רבא's Rava's idea is much
more conceptual than אביי's. Abaye's. אביי Abaye just said, okay, it was
a case where it didn't have a chance to be in the
air. And רבא Rava says, no, the fact that someone was able
to grab it means it's as if it wasn't really ever going
to land. Well, if it wasn't ever going to really land, then
the air space isn't like the חצר chatzer anymore. Can I ask
a detail? Sure. So, הזבל היוצא מן התנור ומן הכירה והקולט. hazvel
hayotzei min hatannur umin hakirah vehakolet. So we've been trans- we had
been translating זבל zevel earlier as cow manure, right, as opposed to
other things. But here זבל's zevel's coming from the תנור tannur or
the כירה. kirah. So, right, so זבל zevel might just be waste
in general, or it may be זבל, zevel, comma, היוצא מן התנור
ומן הכירה והקולט, hayotzei min hatannur umin hakirah vehakolet, right? It depends
on how you parse it. It could be... But the מחלוקת machloket
about catching the- like, we left the תנור tannur as... right, it's
not interesting. Not interesting to us. It's not interesting to us because
what we're really discussing now is רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא's Rabbi Yosei
beRabbi Chanina's opinion. Can we disprove רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא's Rabbi Yosei
beRabbi Chanina's position? That is, he says חצירו של אדם קונה לו
שלא מדעתו, chatzeiro shel adam koneh lo shelo midato, and we want
to say, well, are there other ברייתות beraitot that contradict his position
or not? And that's-
that's about what part of this is our משנה, mishnah, right? Right.
Exactly. Because the משנה mishnah said that it belongs to the משכיר,
maskir, the בעל הבית, baal habayit, exactly. And if the- if it
belongs... right. And it doesn't say anything about- the משנה mishnah says
only what comes out of the oven and the stove belongs. Right.
But not whatever is grabbed out of midair. Okay. But the discussion
is about the windows, much more interesting, especially in the city. Okay,
windows are also important and all of the stuff about היזק ראייה
hezek re'iyah that we've seen in בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, windows become
important. Okay. Unfortunately, we're not going to discuss much of it. We're
not going to discuss much of it. It's not- back into זבל.
zevel. It's a- you know, if we had a תורה שבעל פה
Torah she-be'al peh that was still בעל פה, be'al peh, you know,
we would discuss all sorts of different things not necessarily on the
דף. daf. But that's- that's what we have. We have what's on
the דף. daf. Look- actually, זבל zevel is actually זבל zevel is
extremely important actually, to be fair. It's an important model to understand
something which initially is considered worthless, that is, the owner of the
cow treats the manure as הפקר. hefker. But whoever wants to sell
manure thinks it's very valuable. So that's- it's extraordinarily valuable. It's extraordinarily
valuable, right. But the point- the reason why you're allowed to claim
it is because we assume that when it first comes out that
it's הפקר. hefker. So that's an interesting sort of paradox. Okay, we
have to keep going. We have a lot of גמרא Gemara to
cover.
The price of דף יומי. Daf Yomi. ומי פשיטא ליה לרבא? umi
peshita lei l'Rava?
So who said that that was so obvious to רבא Rava that
רבא Rava can have this complicated, more conceptual approach? והא מיבעיא בעי
ליה לרבא? veha miba'aya ba'ei lei l'Rava?
So because רבא Rava asks this question: זרק ארנקי בפתח זה ויצא
בפתח זה מהו? zarak arnaki befetach zeh veyatza befetach zeh mahu? Someone
threw a wallet at the door, this- and it went out of
this door. מהו? Mahu? So you threw the wallet in through one
door and it went out the other door. So this is a
case here that we're talking about. So אויר avir and it passed
through the חצר chatzer or passed through the house. Okay, so was
he able to acquire it in between? That is, it was going
to land, but it wasn't going to land in this חצר, chatzer,
it was going to land somewhere else. So that's a kind of
a question for רבא. Rava. Or that's really a proof for רבא.
Rava. So מהו? mahu? אויר שאין סופו לנוח כמונח דמי או לאו
כמונח דמי? avir she'ein sofo lanuach k'munach dami o lav k'munach dami?
So is it something that's not actually ever going to rest in
this property, does that consider to be... be resting in this property
or not? That is, how do we understand this whole principle that
something floating in the air is as if it's on the ground?
Is it the whole time it's traveling, it's like it's on the
ground? Or is it only because it was going to eventually land
that while it's in the air you can pretend or imagine that
it will end up on the ground? Okay. So התם לא מיפסק
ולא מידי הכא מיפסק כלי hatam lo mifsak v'lo midi hacha mifsak
kli and that's also the difference. That for אביי, Abaye, the cases
that there's actually a כלי kli in between. There's a difference between
whether it was going to land, if there were no כלי kli
there it was going to land, but here there's actually a הפסק,
hefsek, there's a כלי kli blocking. And that's the kind of a
difference as well. So that's why רבא Rava and אביי Abaye have
that מחלוקת. machloket. There's more to unpack there, but we have to
keep moving. Okay. ושברפת ושבחצר הרי אלו של בעל הבית. v'shebarefet v'shebachatzer
harei eilu shel ba'al habayit. Things that are in the רפת refet
or in the חצר, chatzer, those belong to the בעל הבית. ba'al
habayit. So תרתי אמר אביי הכי קאמר שברפת שבחצר הרי אלו של
בעל הבית. tarti amar Abaye hachi ka'amar shebarefet shebachatzer harei eilu shel
ba'al habayit. So no, you say it like this, not in two
different places, but it's
שברפת שבחצר, shebarefet shebachatzer, it's in the רפת refet that's in the
חצר, chatzer, that belongs to the בעל הבית. ba'al habayit. אמר רב
אשי, amar Rav Ashi, רב אשי Rav Ashi says, זאת אומרת המשכיר
חצרו סתם לא השכיר רפת שבה. zot omeret hamaskir chatzero stam lo
hiskir refet shebah. Someone who rents out his חצר chatzer סתם, stam,
without any specifications, לא השכיר רפת, lo hiskir refet, that means he
didn't rent out the רפת refet because the רפת refet is considered
a separate part from the חצר. chatzer. לא השכיר רפת שבה, lo
hiskir refet shebah, sorry. מתיבי, meiteivei, but isn't there a contradiction? Now
this מתיבי meiteivei is going again on רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא's Rabbi
Yosi b'Rabbi Chanina position, that is, now it's the third attempt to
disprove the principle of חצרו של אדם קונה לו שלא מדעתו. chatzero
shel adam koneh lo shelo m'da'ato. So what does this ברייתא braita
say? This is a ברייתא braita from חולין, Chullin, יוני שובך ויוני
עליה חייבות בשילוח ואסורות בגזל מפני דרכי שלום. yonei shovach v'yonei aliyah
chayavot b'shiluach v'asurot b'gezel mipnei darchei shalom. The doves who live in
a dovecote. Now the idea of a dovecote is that the doves
nest there and the dovecote is built by someone, it belongs to
someone, it's property. The doves are kind of semi-ownerless because the doves
might live in one dovecote one time and they fly around and
they go and nest in a different dovecote. And so that's part
of the halachic problem of dove raising, is that it's somewhat loose
with ownership, gets you into some problems. So יוני שובך ויוני עליה,
yonei shovach v'yonei aliyah, doves of a dovecote and doves who live
in the attic, חייבות בשילוח, chayavot b'shiluach, they're obligated to if you
come across them sitting on their nests of eggs, you have to
do שילוח הקן, shiluach haken, you have to send away the mother
bird from the eggs. ואסורות בגזל, va'asurot b'gezel, and they are prohibited
because of גזל gezel מפני דרכי שלום, mipnei darchei shalom, not because
of actual real גזל, gezel, but we treat it like גזל gezel
because of דרכי שלום, darchei shalom, out of respect for, you know,
communal communal needs. And obviously דרכי שלום, darchei shalom, extensive discussion in
גיטין Gittin and in other places what the parameters of the תקנות
takanot of דרכי שלום darchei shalom were. Okay. ואי איתא להא דאמר
רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא דאמר חצרו של אדם קונה לו שלא מדעתו,
v'ei ita l'ha d'amar Rabbi Yosi b'Rabbi Chanina d'amar chatzero shel adam
koneh lo shelo m'da'ato, if we do have רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא's
Rabbi Yosi b'Rabbi Chanina position that the חצר chatzer of someone could
acquire on their behalf even without their knowledge, קרי כאן כי יקרא,
kari kan ki yikarei, so could you really
say
כי יקרא, ki yikarei,
can you say in that case that you since you've already acquired
it, you own this dove, it's in your property, so does that
mean you're coming across it sort of happenstance? And that's why you
would be obligated to do קן ציפור? kan tzipor? Obviously you don't
have to do שילוח הקן shiluach haken for birds that you own.
If you have a chicken coop and you kept the eggs, you
don't have to, it's not the מצוה mitzvah of שילוח הקן shiluach
haken to shoo away the
שילוח הקן, shiluach haken, קן ציפור, kan tzipor, שילוח הקן, shiluach haken,
קן ציפור, kan tzipor, שילוח הקן shiluach haken because it's, Michael just
told me, okay.
Tell everybody who said that.
Okay. שכוח. shkoach. So פרט למזומן. perat l'mizuman. So the פסוק pasuk
comes to exclude birds that are owned, owned by, have been already
set aside and owned by someone. אמר רבא ביצה ביציאת רובה היא
דאיתחייבה לה בשילוח וקנייה לא קנייה עד דנפלה לחצרו. amar Rava beitiza
bitziat ruba hi d'itchayva lah b'shiluach u'kanyah lo kanyah ad d'nafla l'chatzero.
No,
so רבא Rava solves the problem. Why? Because the obligation to do
the מצוה mitzvah of שילוח shiluach kicks in at the time that
the egg is majority out of the bird, but the acquisition of
קנין חצר kinyan chatzer can only take place once the egg lands
in the nest. So the time period in between when the egg
was being laid and when it could be acquired by the חצר,
chatzer, that's the period in which this applies. That is, there is
a time period, a very minimal time period, when the מצוה mitzvah
of שילוח הקן shiluach haken applies even though the
because the egg remains ownerless. It has not yet been acquired by
the קנין חצר kinyan chatzer and
but it has already
It's a halfway laid egg until it lands. No, no, that this
ברייתא braita is cannot be used to disprove רבי יוסי בר רבי
חנינא. Rabbi Yose bar Rabbi Hanina. They wanted to use this ברייתא
braita to disprove רבי יוסי בר רבי חנינא. Rabbi Yose bar Rabbi
Hanina. Because רבי יוסי בר רבי חנינא Rabbi Yose bar Rabbi Hanina
said חצרו של אדם קונה לו שלא מדעתו, chatzeiro shel adam koneh
lo she'lo m'da'ato,
they would say, oh, but what do you mean? The dove is
sitting there in my dovecote, I'll acquire it without my knowledge so
it will be פטור patur from שילוח הקן. shiluach haken. So comes
רבא Rava and says no, there is a very minimal point at
which there is an obligation for שילוח הקן shiluach haken even though
because the bird remains ownerless or the egg remains ownerless until it
actually lands on the ground. And I own it? No,
you own it only מדרבנן m'drabbanan because of דרכי שלום, darchei shalom,
right? The point is the egg, you own the egg once the
egg lands. But you become חייב... chayav... No, that you
the egg you'll own because of קנין חצר. kinyan chatzer. The birds
you don't own. Birds you only own because of דרכי שלום. darchei
shalom. He also proves that the אויר avir is not part of
the ground. Right, because it's still in the air so to speak.
The egg, right, you can do like a freeze frame in the
air. So at what point do I need to get the egg?
It's on the ground. Correct. And then I'm no longer חייב... chayav...
Correct. But if the bird is in the process of laying the
egg
then and like the egg pops out or whatever, like that's the
moment, right, that's the moment at which you have the מצוה mitzvah
to shoo away the mother. You can imagine sort of at that
point I become חייב chayav in the מצוה, mitzvah, so even once
the egg would land maybe I would still be obligated to shoo
away the mother because the מצוה mitzvah kicked in at that point.
I'm not sure about that. Okay. דהכי תני חייב בשילוח מקמי דתיפול
לחצירה. v'hachi tanni chayav b'shiluach mikamma d'tippol l'chatzeira. So אי הכי, ee
hachi, אמאי אסורות משום גזל? ammai asurot mishum gezel? So if you're
going to tell me that they're obligated in שילוח shiluach because of
this whole sort of technicality about the חצר chatzer that you didn't
really acquire it yet, so then why are they אסורות משום גזל?
asurot mishum gezel? So אמאן, amman, אי בעית אימא לעולם ביצים. ee
bayit eima l'olam habetzim.
So are we talking about אמן, imman, about the mothers, about the
birds themselves? No, we're talking about the eggs. ומדנפק רובא. u'mi-d'nafik rubba.
No, so we're talking about when the eggs had emerged majority emerged
from the mother. דאתו ואייבו de-atayei v'ovei and that's when you're thinking
about them. והשתא דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב, v'hashta d'amar Rav Yehuda
amar Rav, because רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said quoting רב, Rav, אסור
לזכות בביצים כל זמן שהאם רובצת עליהם. assur l'zakot be-betzim kol zman
she'ha'eim rovetzet aleihem.
You cannot acquire the eggs, not just you cannot take the eggs,
but even in a legal sense you cannot acquire the eggs whenever
the mother is still perched on top of them, שנאמר, shene'emar, שלח
תשלח את האם. shale'ach teshale'ach et ha'eim. You have to send away
the mother, והדר את הבנים תקח לך. ve-hadar et habanim tikach lach.
Only then once you have shooed away the mother can you take
the eggs.
אפילו תימא דנפלה לחצר כל היכא דאיהו מצי זכי ליה, afilu teima
d'nafla l'chatzeir kol heicha d'ihu matzi zakhei lei, זכי ליה חצרו. zakhei
lei chatzeiro.
So then at that point the חצר chatzer could acquire it on
your behalf only after that point. וכל היכא דאיהו לא מצי זכי
ליה חצרו נמי לא זכי ליה, ve-chol heicha d'ihu lo matzi zakhei
lei chatzeiro nami lo zakhei lei, and if I'm unable to acquire
it on my own then obviously my חצר chatzer can't do it
for me either. This is a similar principle to what we saw
in נזיר, Nazir, the general guiding principle about שליחות, shlichut, anything that
you can do yourself you can make a שליח, shaliach, but if
you can't do it yourself you can't make a שליח shaliach to
do it. So similarly here the way חצר chatzer is being treated
is like a שליח. shaliach. זכי ליה. zakhei lei. אי הכי, ee
hachi, אסורות בגזל מפני דרכי שלום. asurot be-gezel mipnei darchei shalom. No,
no, no, the only reason they're prohibited for being stolen is because
of דרכי שלום. darchei shalom. אי דשלחה גזל מעליא היא, ee d'shalcha
gezel ma'alya hi,
but if you send it away at that point it becomes like
real גזל gezel because at that point once you send away the
mother and you already acquired the eggs then you own the eggs.
Okay. אי דלא שלחה, ee d'lo shalcha, הא בעי שילוח, ha ba'ei
shiluach, so
but then why would you have to send it away? If you
don't own it that's when you have to do שילוח הקן shiluach
haken but then when you're picking up the eggs then you already
own it, so it becomes kind of a catch-22. So what are
we talking about? בקטן דלאו בר שילוח הוא. be-katan d'lav bar shiluach
hu. So it must be a קטן katan who's not obligated in
the מצוה mitzvah of שילוח הקן, shiluach haken, but a קטן katan
can have certain financial ownership. So קטן בר דרכי שלום הוא? katan
bar darchei shalom hu? But is a קטן katan really someone who's
included within the תקנה takkanah of דרכי שלום? darchei shalom? הכי קאמר,
hachi ka'amar, אביו של קטן חייב להחזיר לו מפני דרכי שלום. aviv
shel katan chayav lehachazir lo mipnei darchei shalom. No,
so the parents have an obligation to return things that their children
stole that are stolen under the תקנות takkanot of דרכי שלום. darchei
shalom. That is things that are really considered ownerless and only מפני
דרכי שלום mipnei darchei shalom is there an obligation
to pay. How much responsibility do the parents have for crimes and
sins that their children do, certainly financial liabilities, and then also for
מצוות mitzvot and things like that as well. We'll pick up with
the next משנה, mishna, the second-to-last line of ק"ב עמוד א'. kuf
bet amud aleph. Yeah, David. Thinking about in contemporary times, what do
we have? We have chickens that are sitting on some kind of
a...
what do you call that stuff?
Mesh, mesh. Wire mesh, so that the eggs fall down, right? So
then this would not apply, right? Well, it doesn't apply to chickens
anyway because chickens are owned birds, it's פרט למונח. prat lemunach. The
מצווה mitzvah only applies to an ownerless wild bird.
So now the question becomes doves. Doves are obviously ownerless wild, or
are they... well, they're semi-wild. That's exactly the interesting liminal case of
doves, because the doves are somewhat domesticated, but they're still basically considered
ownerless, the ownership is only at the דרבנן derabbanan level.
The fascinating question about שילוח הקן shiluach haken is that in general
most פוסקים poskim will say that you're encouraged to do the מצווה.
mitzvah. It also only applies to כשר kosher birds. We know nowadays
that most communities will only eat birds that they actually have a
continuous מסורה mesorah that that's been a bird that people will eat.
There's so many birds that there is such a tradition for, but
there are many birds that there's not a tradition for. Well, turkey
is something else. But something like, let's say, a robin, or a
blue jay, or an oriole, something like that. Are they כשר kosher
birds? Why not? Are they? So that's the question. So those are
birds that certainly are not
vicious raptor דורס dores type birds, but they're also not birds that
we have an active מסורה mesorah to eat them. But the general
principle is that for שילוח הקן shiluach haken we're more expansive in
our understanding of what counts as a כשר kosher bird because the
מצוות עשה mitzvat aseh to do is also comes with the מצוות
לא תעשה, mitzvat lo ta'aseh, לא תקח האם על הבנים. lo tikach
ha'em al habanim. So whenever I have to avoid a מצוות לא
תעשה, mitzvat lo ta'aseh, I'm actually being מחמיר machmir by including more
birds within the purview of the מצווה, mitzvah, but there's been a
lot written about that. Okay. Thinking you run on a robin egg
then? Well, robin egg, but that's... we're not going to eat the
egg, right? People do the מצווה mitzvah now because of the ברכה,
bracha, דהארכת ימים, deha'arachta yamim, not because of actually getting the eggs,
which is very ironic. Anyway, okay, we'll continue with the משנה. mishna.
המשכיר בית לחברו, Hamaskir bayit lechavero, someone rented the house to their
friend, לשנה. leshana. Someone rented a house, and now remember, we have
to think back to times of the משנה, mishna, mishnaic times, every
year had the potential to be a leap year. In the month
of אדר, Adar, they would determine whether פסח Pesach was gonna be
early enough or late enough, and by the time ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh came at the end of the month of אדר, Adar, the
בית דין beit din would decide is this going to be second
אדר, Adar, or is this going to be ניסן? Nissan? So, the
person made a rental agreement to rent out a house for one
year. המשכיר בית לחברו לשנה, Hamaskir bayit lechavero leshana, נתעברה השנה. nit'abra
hashana. And then they added in a thirteenth month. Now, who has
to pay rent for that month? Okay, that's a question, נתעברה השנה.
nit'abra hashana. So נתעברה לשוכר. nit'abra lesocher. It is added on for
the שוכר. socher. Why? Because the agreement was for a year, and
this is still one year. It's a year that happens to have
thirteen months, but it's a year nonetheless. Always enter into twelve month
leases! Well, השכיר לו לחודשים, hiskir lo lechodashim, if he rented it
month by month, נתעברה השנה, nit'abra hashana, נתעברה למשכיר. nit'abra lamaskir. Then
in that case, the added month benefits the משכיר maskir because he
gets a thirteenth month's rent because the rental agreement was month by
month. Seems pretty straightforward. Okay.
מעשה בציפורי, Ma'aseh beTzippori, now there's a case in ציפורי. Tzippori. Talking
about קן ציפור, kahn tzippor, now מעשה בציפורי. ma'aseh beTzippori. That's a...
well, the קן ציפור kahn tzippor was just in the גמרא, Gemara,
it wasn't in the משנה. mishna. Okay. מעשה בציפורי באחד ששכר מרחץ
מחברו, Ma'aseh beTzippori be'echad shesachar merchatz mechabero, someone rented a bathhouse from
his friend for how much? בשנים עשר זהב לשנה, Bishneim asar zahav
leshana, the rental agreement stipulated twelve golden dinars for the year, מדינר
זהב לחודש, midinar zahav lachodesh, one gold dinar per month. So now
it's redundant, but it's unclear whether it was a yearly agreement or
a monthly agreement.
ובא מעשה לפני רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Uva ma'aseh lifnei Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel, ולפני רבי יוסי. velifnei Rabbi Yosi. Interesting, does that mean
it was two court cases, or does it mean they were both
sitting on a בית דין beit din together? Not so clear from
the משנה. mishna. ואמרו, Ve'amru, they said, יחלוקו את חודש העיבור. yachloku
et chodesh ha'ibur.
They split the liability for the month, the rental month, because of
the ambiguity in the agreement. The arrangement was unclear, so the שוכר
socher should only have to pay half the rent. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says, מעשה לסתור. ma'aseh listotei.
So the מעשה ma'aseh seems to contradict the principle. Why? Because you
should normally say go by the last clause in the agreement if
it was two contradictory statements, you go by the second one presumably.
So חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני. chasorei mechasra vehachi katani. We should change
the way the משנה Mishnah should be read. ואי אמר לו בשנים
עשר זהובים לשנה מדינר זהב לחודש, ve'ei amar lo bishneim asar zehuvim
leshana midinar zahav lechodesh,
if the agreement was twelve golden dinars for the year, one golden
dinar per month, יחלוקו, yachaloku, they should split it. ומעשה נמי, uma'aseh
nami, and there was a case בצפורי beTzippori באחד ששכר מרחץ מחברו
be'echad shesachar merchatz mechaveiro בשנים עשר זהובים לשנה מדינר זהב לחודש, bishneim
asar zehuvim leshana midinar zahav lechodesh, and there was a case of
exactly that, ובא מעשה לפני רבן שמעון בן גמליאל ולפני רבי יוסי
ואמרו יחלוקו את חודש העיבור. uva ma'aseh lifnei Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
velifnei Rabbi Yosi ve'amru yachaloku et chodesh ha'ibur. And so first the
משנה Mishnah should state the law, split it, and then should say
and there was such a case and it came before them and
they said split it and it wouldn't contradict. Okay. אמר רב, Amar
Rav, Rav said, אי הוי התם הוה
יהבינא ליה כולה למשכיר. ei havei hatam hava yahavina lei kulei lemashkir.
Does חסורי מחסרא chasorei mechasra actually really mean because the ruling was
missing? What does חסורי מחסרא... chasorei mechasra... you don't actually really mean
that like our משנה Mishnah is wrong and that something needs... there's
a major debate how to understand it as if that's what it
says. The generally understood way to read חסורי מחסרא chasorei mechasra is
the משנה Mishnah means what we're telling you what it means. The
legal meaning of this משנה Mishnah is as we're saying, not actually
amend the text of the משנה, Mishnah, but revise how you understand
what the משנה Mishnah means. Now in some cases that fits very
nicely like here. All they're telling us here is imagine the משנה
Mishnah said the ruling before the case. But in other cases, the
best example I can think of now, the third פרק perek of
שבת, Shabbat, פרק כירה Perek Kira starts with a very confusing משנה
Mishnah that גמרא Gemara goes through many attempts to try to do
חסורי מחסרא chasorei mechasra and it gets very complex because of that,
and it's kind of interchanging all different variables trying to sort through
the details there, and even the ראשונים Rishonim had a headache trying
to figure it out, very long בעל המאור Ba'al HaMa'or about it.
Oh, so you don't think it means the text was corrupt and
we have a... right, so I was just saying there's basically two
approaches. There's what I just said which is sort of the more
traditionalist approach and then a more...
again it depends on what authority you think אמוראים Amoraim have over
the משנה. Mishnah. That is, could the rulings of the בתי דין
batei din of the אמוראים Amoraim come to actually say no the
משנה Mishnah is just a record of the הלכות, halachot, we're changing
the הלכה halacha or we're revising the הלכה halacha for clarity, so
we need to adjust what the text of the משנה Mishnah means
as well? So it's unclear. You know when you see חסורי מחסרא
chasorei mechasra does that mean like go back to my משנה Mishnah
book and draw a line through things and reorganize it? That's a
big question. So thank goodness that we didn't do that because now
we can see both versions, the original version and the revised version,
which gives us a wealth of information. Okay.
So whatever it means I'm glad we didn't do it that way
to actually amend the text. Okay. אמר רב, Amar Rav, Rav said,
אי הוי התם הוה יהבינא ליה כולה למשכיר. ei havei hatam hava
yahavina lei kulei lemashkir. So what do you mean? If it would
have come to me, says רב, Rav, I would have said all
of the money should go to the משכיר. mashkir. To the משכיר,
mashkir, to the renter. Why? Presumably the renter has...
he owns the land. Not the
renter, the renter-outer. I'm sorry, I need to clarify. The משכיר, mashkir,
the owner is the one who is renting out the property. Why?
Because he owns the property. He has a חזקה chazaka on the
property. Now that, okay, now what's interesting, what do we have here?
We have competing two חזקות. chazakot. We have חזקת ממון chazkat mammon
on the part of the שוכר. socher. I have my cash. And
we have
a חזקה chazaka of property on the part of the משכיר. mashkir.
So according to רב, Rav, the חזקה chazaka of ownership of the
property says fine if you want to live on my
land you got to pay, and the משכיר mashkir always has the
more powerful claim. So מאי קמשמע לן, mai kamashma lan, what did
that come to teach? תפוס לשון אחרון. tefus lashon acharon. That means
grab onto the second clause. That is the clause that said it
goes by month by month. האמר רב, Ha'amar Rav, and that's what
רב Rav said.
So
חדא זימנא דאמר רב הונא אמרי בי רב, Chada zimna de'amar Rav
Huna amrei bei Rav, there was one time that what did רב
הונא Rav Huna say, they said in רב's Rav school,
אסטירה מאה. asteira me'ah.
So אסטירה, asteira, a coin that's called אסטירה asteira was one hundred.
That's what they said in רב's Rav school. So מאי מאה, mai
me'ah, what does it mean a hundred? So מאי מאה, mai me'ah,
what do you mean a hundred? So מאי אסטירה, mai asteira, they
should have said what's an אסטירה, asteira, meaning I know what a
hundred is, a hundred whatever, a hundred דינר. dinar. Okay. So אסטירה
אי מהתם... asteira ei mehatam... מאי מעות... mai ma'ot... מעות ma'ot means
what? No,
מאי, mai, the מעות, ma'ot, those coins. Right,
right, the coins. מאה מאי. me'ah mai. So מאה מאי אסטירה. me'ah
mai asteira. So don't say it, meaning why did it go back
and forth? So אסטירה אי מהתם, asteira ei mehatam, if you would
have learned it from there. פירושי קא מפרש. perushi ka mefaresh. I
thought it was just an explanation. So קא משמע לן, ka mashma
lan, that's why it comes to say that they had to repeat
it both times. That is, not just אסתירא Astira מעא ma'a
and מעא ma'a אסתירא. astira. You say it both ways to clarify
that it's an equivalence between two different coinages and not that it's
just how much this one coin is worth. That is, so does
that mean רב Rav says in general תפוס לשון אחרון? tefus lashon
acharon? Not necessarily. Okay. ושמואל אמר. uShmuel amar. So שמואל Shmuel understands
this case differently. שמואל Shmuel says, אמר בבא באמצע חודש עסקינן. amar
beba be'emtza chodesh askinan. No, the reason they split it is because—wait,
let me explain it here. Yeah. Is that if he said an
אסתירא astira is a מעא, ma'a, meaning he said this is an
אסתירא astira מעא. ma'a. Then the guy has to pay מעא. ma'a.
Right. But מעא ma'a אסתירא, astira, then he has to pay אסתירא.
astira. So that's the way they're taking it.
Which means always תפוס לשון אחרון. tefus lashon acharon. That's how—fine, it's
a proof that רב Rav says תפוס לשון אחרון. tefus lashon acharon.
Fine, okay. That works. Okay. ושמואל אמר. uShmuel amar. The point is
I want to get to שמואל'ס—שמואל disagrees. So שמואל Shmuel says, שמואל
אמר בבא באמצע חודש עסקינן. Shmuel amar beba be'emtza chodesh askinan. The
reason why רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel and רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi פסקן pasken that you should split it is because—because
the month.
Because the משכיר maskir showed up to collect the rent in the
middle of the thirteenth month. Okay. אבל בא בתחילת חודש כולה למשכיר.
Aval ba betchilat chodesh kulei lamaskir. If he would have showed up
at the beginning of the month, שמואל Shmuel says then he would
be able to claim the entire month. That is why? Because for
the first half of the month, no one claimed the rental cost
and he was able to sit there and he has the חזקה
chazakah that it was part of his year-long agreement. Only by the
time that the משכיר maskir shows up and claims it can he
make the claim. So it goes like רב Rav that the—the משכיר
maskir has the stronger claim, but he can still only claim from
the point where he shows up to make the claim and not
any further. And that's why שמואל—שמואל'ס like a middle position almost about
that. And that שמואל'ס Shmuel's position presumably should be the הלכה. halachah.
Usually we follow שמואל בדיני. Shmuel bedinei. Okay. So בא בסוף חודש,
ba besof chodesh, if he shows at the end of the month,
כולה לשוכר. kulei lasocher. Then the entire month goes to the שוכר.
socher. It's like he defaulted on his ability to collect the rent
for that month, the משכיר. maskir. And it rolled in so to
speak—rolled into the whole year for free. So מי אמר שמואל לא
אמרינן תפוס לשון אחרון? mi amar Shmuel lo amrinan tefus lashon acharon?
Does שמואל Shmuel not say just go by the last clause of
the agreement, תפוס לשון אחרון? tefus lashon acharon? Follow the last clause?
והא רב ושמואל דאמרי תרווייהו. veha Rav uShmuel de'amri tarvaihu. But רב
Rav and שמואל Shmuel both agree in this case, כור בשלושים אני
מוכר לך. kor bishloshim ani mocher lach. If I'm selling you one
כור kor for thirty, יכול לחזור בו אפילו בסאה אחרונה. yachol lachzor
bo afilu bese'ah achronah. Either of them could renege on the deal
even until the last—until the last סאה. se'ah. But כור בשלושים סאה
בסלע. kor bishloshim se'ah besela. But if the agreement was I'm selling
a כור kor for thirty, but each סאה se'ah for one סלע.
sela. So אני מוכר לך, ani mocher lach, ראשון ראשון קנה. rishon
rishon kanah. But then the purchase goes one by one. And that
is רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel both agree in that case that
you would say תפוס לשון אחרון. tefus lashon acharon. Okay. התם טעמא
מאי? Hatam ta'ama mai? Why is the reason there? משום דתפיס. Mishum
detafis. That—no, the reason why they said that is because at that
point you're actually taking the grain סאה בסאה. se'ah bese'ah. I fill
up my bag one סאה se'ah and I put it on the
truck and I take another bag and I fill it up and
put it on the truck. Just like the guy showing up. Right.
But—so the point at which you can claim or cut off the
deal is only—so if the agreement was a כור, kor, only once
the entire כור kor has been transported am I going to be
able to—not be able to back away from the deal. And that's
the difference. So הכא נמי דתפיס. hacha nami detafis. Maybe this case
is also like you were תופס tofes the money or in that
case.
Okay. ורב נחמן אמר. veRav Nachman amar. So basically since קרקע בחזקת
בעליה קיימת. karka bechezkat be'aleha kayemet. So
therefore what? In—הכא נמי hacha nami this is the case of the
rental, right? In the case of rental, right. So דתפיס. detafis.
No, so this is the different claim. This is now to say
that either no matter how you resolve it, presumably that it was
still in the middle of the month but that he actually already
grabbed the money. And at that point, that's why he can't be
forced to back it up. Right, meaning the renter has—has his money
for the month past. So then
the—quote unquote—the משכיר maskir has his half of the money. Right. But
otherwise it would have been a normal case, then he would have
said תפוס לשון אחרון. tefus lashon acharon. Is that it? Right. Because
in general they say תפוס לשון אחרון tefus lashon acharon and they
also say that in the case where you actually have control of
whatever it is that's being transferred that that's why it gets cut
off bit by bit rather than being treated as a whole. Okay.
Because otherwise you would be able to say the משכיר maskir could
even claim the whole month, right? The point is that it was—דתפיס.
detafis. He had already grabbed it at that point. Okay. So ורב
נחמן אמר. veRav Nachman amar. רב נחמן Rav Nachman interprets the משנה
Mishnah even a third way. Not like רב Rav and not like
שמואל. Shmuel רב נחמן אמר קרקע בחזקת בעליה קיימת. Rav Nachman amar
karka bechezkat be'aleha kayemet. No, the משכיר maskir always has rights for
the full rental agreement. Now what, רב נחמן Rav Nachman is just
disagreeing with רבן שמעון בן גמליאל? Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel? So some
of the ראשונים Rishonim suggest no, it must be that רב נחמן
Rav Nachman is saying the משנה Mishnah preserves the position of סומכוס
Sumchus like we've seen many times before. סומכוס Sumchus says ממון המוטל
בספק יחלוקו, Mammon hamutal besafek yachloku, right? רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel said יחלוקו. yachloku. Nonetheless,
now that we've agreed that we פוסקן pasken like רבנן, Rabbanan, so
רב נחמן's Rav Nachman position is that we should say קרקע בחזקת
בעליה קיימת Karka bechezkat be'alei hakayam and the הלכה halakha should be
like רב נחמן Rav Nachman because we follow like רבנן Rabbanan and
not like סומכוס. Sumchus. Okay.
So מאי קמשמע לן, Mai kamashmalan, so what does that come to
teach us about תפוס לשון אחרון? Tfos lashon achron? So תפוס לשון
אחרון Tfos lashon achron היינו דרב. hainu deRav. So the תפוס לשון
אחרון Tfos lashon achron goes like רב, Rav, why? דאף על גב
דאפיך, de'af al gav de'afich, even if you switched it, right? No,
that was the question, right? I mean that's the question, if you
switch it, we already like רב, Rav, we know where רב Rav
stands, we say ah, so אף על גב דאפיך, af al gav
de'afich,
so even if you switch it, so מפיך, mafich, so then you
even if you switched it.
That is, excuse me, I'm sorry, I'm losing my voice a little
bit.
So even if you would switch the order, that is if the
monthly agreement came first and then the yearly agreement. If it's just
that it's an ambiguous agreement and we don't say תפוס לשון אחרון,
Tfos lashon achron, then you would say the ambiguity is inherent in
the relationship and whoever has the חזקה chazakah is able to make
the claim, in that case the משכיר maskir has the beneficial standing
in the agreement. But if you say the whole point of this
is to teach you תפוס לשון אחרון, Tfos lashon achron, which is
רב's Rav position, then תפוס לשון אחרון Tfos lashon achron should apply
differently if the clauses were switched, if the yearly agreement came second,
because then you would say תפוס לשון אחרון Tfos lashon achron goes
by a yearly agreement then the שוכר socher is the one who
benefits not the משכיר. maskir. Okay. בעו מיניה מרבי ינאי. Ba'u minei
meRabbi Yannai. So they asked רבי ינאי, Rabbi Yannai, שוכר socher אמר
נתתי, amar natati, the שוכר socher says I already paid rent, ומשכיר
אומר לא נטלתי, umaskir omer lo natalti, and the משכיר maskir says
I didn't get the rent. This is a common case, right? אמיליה
הוי ראיה, Amilah havi raya, who has to bring proof in this
case? סיימא אי בתוך זמנו, Seima i betoch zemano, if it was
already, it was before the deadline, so תנינא, tanina, that's the case
of the משנה. Mishnah. אי לאחר זמנו תנינא, I le'achar zemano tanina,
then we also have
a משנה. Mishnah. דתנן, Detnan, what does the משנה Mishnah say? The
משנה Mishnah in בכורות, Bechorot, מת האב בתוך שלשים יום, met ha'av
betoch sheloshim yom, if the father died within 30 days, that is,
this is a case of פדיון הבן pidyon haben very tragically, the
father of a newborn baby dies in the 30 days before the
baby is נפדה, nifdeh, so בחזקת שלא נפדה, bechezkat shelo nifdeh, the
assumption is that the baby has not yet been
redeemed עד שיביא ראיה שנפדה, ad sheyavi raya shenifdeh, until you bring
proof, because it's לא בזמנו, lo bazmano, it's not the time hasn't
arrived yet. So it's like we have a general assumption by monetary
things, you don't pay until the deadline. You want to keep your
money until the last minute, so you don't pay until the... So
you actually could do the פדיון הבן pidyon haben before the 30th
day? Presumably you could pay the כהן kohen in advance so that
the פדיון pidyon kicks in before the 30th day, but the מצוה,
mitzvah, at least the assumption in the משנה Mishnah in בכורות, Bechorot,
I'm not sure about the details of that... Conditional, okay? There is
a way to do it in a conditional way where you actually
give the money in advance, I think there is a way... It's
yours assuming now, assuming the baby lives... Right, if the baby lives
and if whatever and that it should transfer in such a way,
right. Now again, how much and and the fact that פדיון בכור
pidyon bechor is basically much more like treated like a monetary kind
of a case, it's much less ritualized מצוה, mitzvah, kind of interesting.
Okay. לאחר שלשים יום, Le'achar sheloshim yom, if the father died after
30 days, בחזקת שנפדה, bechezkat shenifdeh, עד שיאמרו לו שלא נפדה, ad
sheyomru lo shelo nifdeh, and if the father died after 30 days,
the assumption is that the baby has been redeemed until the כהנים
kohanim bring proof that there was no פדיון הבן. pidyon haben. Of
course, it's a big challenge, every... what, you know, he also has
the claim, you know, just because none of the כהנים kohanim in
the neighborhood know that he did פדיון הבן, pidyon haben, he could
have done with some other כהן. kohen. So that also further complicates
things, it gives him, you know, בכורות Bechorot cases many of the
best cases of המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah, that
is the כהן kohen very often is the one who has to
bring a proof that he needs to be paid. So similar to
how we deal with wages...
Right.
So that משנה Mishnah seems to indicate about paying before the deadline
and after the deadline, it should be comparable to the rent, the
גמרא gemara says אי בתוך זמנו, i betoch zemano, if the time
is not arrived yet for payment,
then you're going to believe that he hasn't paid. If the time
has not, if the deadline for the rent to be due has
not yet arrived, we assume he has not paid, right, and then
the guy says I paid, and the burden of proof will be
on the
שוכר. socher. It's actually, it's a disincentive to paying your rent early
because paying your rent early is unusual. So if you pay your
rent early, you have to be able to prove it. Exactly, you
both have a burden of proof and you don't have the money
in your hands. Right, that's why we have checks... Well, checks and
keeping your checkbook and looking online are
all... וצריכא ביומי דמשלם זימניה. v'tzricha b'yomei d'mashlem zimneih.
What happens if the father dies and the child's not been redeemed?
The child has an obligation to do it himself. Oh, he can
do it? Yeah, an
adult can do
it too. What? The mother? The brother? No. Mother, I said. The
mother for
פדיון הבן pidyon haben cannot do it. Really?
גמרא Gemara in קידושין. Kiddushin. She's not obligated in the מצוה. mitzvah.
It's a discussion in the גמרא Gemara in קידושין. Kiddushin. I won't
tell Tzipi, don't worry. The first was a girl anyway. So there
you go, no problem. I mean פדיון הבן pidyon haben is so
unusual these days especially because C-sections are very common and very many
לויים Leviim and כהנים Kohanim have all mixed, you know, together. So,
you know, we have lots of lots of reasons why פדיון הבן
pidyon haben is a very unusual situation. My first son was C-section,
the second born was the one we did the פדיון. pidyon. So
there you go, okay. So it's very exciting. So just make sure
you don't pay too early. You pay the day of, right? לא
צריכא ביומי דמשלם זימניה. lo tzericha b'yomei d'mashlim zimnei. So what about
if he shows up on the day that it's due? מי עבידי
אינשי דפרעי ביומי דמשלם זימניה או לא? mi avidi inishei d'parai b'yomei
d'mashlim zimnei o lo? Are people accustomed to actually pay on the
day that the debt is due or no? אמר להו רבי יוחנן
תניתוה. amar lehu Rabbi Yochanan tanituha.
Don't they have to pay on the day the debt is due?
They have to pay, but the question is like can you then
assume, does the חזקה chazakah switch at that point? Like now that
today is the deadline, has the assumption immediately switched to yes, you
are assumed to have paid or does it wait until the next
day, the day after the deadline? Okay. רבי יוחנן תניתוה: Rabbi Yochanan
tanituha: שכיר בזמנו נשבע ונוטל. sachir bizmano nishba venotel. שכיר הוא דרמו
רבנן שבועה עליה משום דבעל הבית טרוד. sachir hu d'ramu rabanan shvua
alai mishum d'baal habayit tarud.
Let's stop here because we'll pick this up with whoever's teaching on
שבת. Shabbat. All right. I'm going away for שבת Shabbat for a
שבתון, Shabbaton, but everyone should have a wonderful שבת Shabbat and...